<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> <!-- -*- nxml -*- -->

<article>
<sect1>
	<title align="center">	Section 1 - Introduction</title>
<sect2>
	<title >1.1       Scope of report</title>

<para>The purpose of this report is to assess the levels of indemnity insurance cover in place as at  {{EffectiveDate}}, regarding the risks covered as well as the quantum of cover, in respect of the {{FundName}} </para>
 
<para>It is not possible to make a fully informed recommendation regarding the level of indemnity insurance cover necessary without carrying out a comprehensive risk assessment in respect of the Fund. The recommendations made in this report are therefore based on the information provided, and on the assumption that the Fund follows the guidelines and principles set out in the Financial Services Board’s (“FSB”) Circular PF 130.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>1.2       Need for Indemnity Insurance</title>

<para>Regulation 30(2)(u) of the Pension Funds Act (“the Act”) requires the rules of a fund to provide for “the policy of insurance effected to indemnify the pension fund against losses owing to the dishonesty or fraud of any of its officials, or such other indemnification as the Registrar may allow”.</para>

<para>Retirement funds’ financial statements must contain a certification by the Trustees that they have “ensured that fidelity cover was maintained. The cover was deemed adequate and in compliance with the rules of the fund”. Circular PF 130 requires that the Trustees carefully consider the quantum of indemnity insurance cover to ensure that it is appropriate and, where necessary, to take expert advice in that regard.</para>

<para>Circular PF 130 also requires that the Trustees should have indemnity insurance themselves, either provided by the fund or by the sponsor of the fund. The Trustees should also require that each service provider to the fund has adequate insurance cover, so that the Fund’s rights of recourse against those service providers are safeguarded.</para>

<para>The contents of Circular PF 130 make it clear that the Trustees are responsible for ensuring that the Fund has adequate insurance cover, that they should seek professional advice if necessary, and that they would be held responsible if the Fund was found to be under-insured.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>1.3       Information supplied</title>
<para> The following information was supplied in respect of the Fund by the Principal Officer.</para>

<para>·        Indemnity insurance policy documentation including the latest renewal schedules and cover details;</para>

<para>·        an insurance certificate and a copy of the insurance policy” (“the Policy”).</para>
<para> ·        The latest copies of the Funds’ annual financial statements.  </para>
<para> ·        The latest data available at {{EffectiveDate}} of the: </para>
<para> ·      total number of members; </para>
<para> ·      total annual contributions; </para>
<para> ·      total investment holdings; </para>
<para> ·      top ten insured amounts payable on death; and </para>
<para> ·      top ten Members’ shares of Fund.  </para>
<para>Extracts from the information listed above are shown in Appendix A.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title align="center">Section 2 - Policy</title>
<sect2>
<title>2.1       Summary of Policy</title>

<para>The latest renewal schedule and cover details are shown in Appendix A.</para>
<para> The Policy provides that the insurer indemnifies the Fund in respect of losses arising from Defined Events that occur as a consequence of Wrongful Acts of Officers of the Fund. The more important terms of the Policy are summarised below.</para>
</sect2>
<sect3>
<title>2.1.1    An Officer is defined as any of the following who provides services to or for the Insured (Fund)</title>

<para> “a present or past committee member, individual, manager, trustee, administrator, third party service provider, controller, principal officer, treasurer, clerk, employee or agent of the employer company”.  </para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>2.1.2    A Wrongful Act is defined inter alia as:</title>

<para>“Any actual or alleged breach of duty, statutory duty, or trust, neglect, error, misstatement, misleading statement, omission, defamation, injuria, unintentional breach of confidentiality or other act wrongfully committed, omitted or attempted by an officer and which arises by reason of their being an officer of the Insured …”</para>

<para>“Wrongful Act” is defined to exclude acts of theft, fraud, dishonesty and computer crime committed by an Officer, which are covered under another definition in the Policy.  “Wrongful Act” may therefore be considered to be negligence. </para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>2.1.3    Defined Events are defined to include:</title>

<para>a)     Negligence. Any claim first made against any Officer during the period of insurance resulting from any Wrongful Act committed by an Officer;</para>

<para>b)     Theft, Fraud and Dishonesty committed by an Officer which results in loss of money or property of the Fund or causes direct financial loss to the Fund; and</para>

<para>c)     Computer Crime resulting in a loss directly arising from fraudulent or dishonest entry of data or change of data or programmes within the Officer’s computer system.</para>

<para>In summary, the Fund is insured against any loss incurred as a result of the negligence, theft, fraud or dishonesty of an Officer.</para>
</sect3>
<sect2>
<title>2.2       Comments on terms and conditions of policies</title>

<para>The Policy currently in force indemnifies the Fund against defined events arising from Wrongful Acts committed by Officers of the Fund. The Policy does not personally indemnify the Officers of the Fund.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title align="center">Section 3 – Determining adequate cover</title>
<sect2>
<title>3.1       Responsibility of Trustees</title>

<para>It is the responsibility of the Trustees of the Fund to ensure that indemnity insurance cover is in place and that it is adequate.  In the event of a fraud or Wrongful Act of one of the Officers of the Fund, the first step would be to attempt to recover the damages from that Officer. If that Officer is not insured or is otherwise unable to compensate the Fund (within the terms of the Policy), and the limit of indemnity of the Policy is insufficient, the Fund could suffer a loss due to being under-insured. The Trustees could become personally liable for such loss, even though they had nothing to do with the Wrongful Act giving rise to the loss.</para>

<para>In the event that the Trustees are considered responsible for any uninsured loss, it is likely that compensation for such loss would be sought, firstly, from the Trustees appointed by the Fund’s sponsor or administrator.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>3.2       Assessing the risks</title>

<para>In order to determine whether the cover is adequate, an assessment should be made of the potential risks facing the Fund.</para>

<para>One method of assessing potential risks would be to consider the events that could give rise to a financial loss, and then estimate the maximum amount of loss that might arise from such event. Such assessment can be made by considering the different events that could lead to claims under the Policy.</para>


<para>Claims may arise as a result of:</para>

<para>·        errors and omissions in Section 14 transfers;</para>

<para>·        administrative errors;</para>

<para>·        fraud;</para>

<para>·        failure of computers or computer systems;</para>

<para>·        loss of data;</para>

<para>·        conflicts of interest;</para>

<para>·        breach of fiduciary duty; and</para>

<para>·        payment of incorrect benefits, or payment to incorrect persons.</para>

<para>For each possible reason for a financial loss, the Trustees must consider the potential to recover part or all of that loss from the Officer or third party responsible for that loss.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>3.3       Losses due to Negligence</title>

<para>Negligence can lead to failure to perform necessary tasks, or excessive delay in performing those tasks. Possible reasons for claims arising due to negligence are considered below.</para>
<sect3>
<title>3.3.1    Investments</title>

<para>Failure to promptly execute a Member’s instruction to change portfolios, or investment of a Member’s assets in the wrong portfolio, can lead to significant losses to a Fund.  If members are given a choice of investing in a wide range of portfolios, this risk is increased.</para>

<para>Stock-market volatility can lead to significant drops in Members’ investment values over a short period. For example, from 1 September 2008 to 1 November 2008 the JSE All Share Index fell by 24%, and the value of many equity portfolios used by pension funds dropped by similar amounts. Failure to promptly implement a Member’s disinvestment instruction before such a drop in market values could lead to a liability to compensate the Member for this loss.</para>

<para>That is, during a period of high market volatility, a loss of 20% of a Member’s investment value could arise from a 2-month delay in realising that investment.</para>

<para>In May 2003 the JSE All Share Index rose by 14% and the investment value of many pension-fund balanced portfolios increased by similar amounts.  Failure to promptly invest monies received by a Fund could lead to a loss of 14% of the monies to be invested over a single month. This applies not only to monthly contributions for individual members, but to the total contributions received for a Participating Employer, or money received by the Fund on Section 14 transfer.</para>

<para>Investment delays could affect all the Members selecting a specific investment portfolio.  There is the possibility of delays in the investment of Section 14 transfer values received, or transfer values paid, with amounts being held in non-interest-bearing accounts for longer than necessary.</para>

<para>With the highest Member Share of R{{TopShare1}} in the Fund, a loss of 20% would represent R{{TopMemberShareLoss}}. It is possible that more than one Member could suffer such a loss.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>3.3.2    Death benefits</title>

<para>Death benefits are reinsured and, in general, limited to the amount paid by the reinsurer. However, if the sum assured is not paid by the reinsurer because, for example, reinsurance premiums had fallen into arrears or details of an individual Member had negligently not been notified to the reinsurer, this may lead to non-payment of a death claim.</para>

<para>In a catastrophic scenario, there could be more than one death in a particular accident (say a fire at the premises of a Participating Employer, or a motor vehicle or aircraft accident), so that the loss could arise from more than one Member.</para>

<para>The risk of a loss is greater when a new Participating Employer commences participation in a Fund.</para>

<para>The highest sum assured is R{{TopDth1}} in the Fund.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>3.3.3    Routine administration</title>

<para>Inaccuracies in administration, accumulated over an extended period, can lead to losses that are initially not noticed. These may include:</para>

<para>·      inaccuracies in pricing of investment units;</para>

<para>·      errors by service providers, for which the particular service provider is unable to compensate a Fund;</para>

<para>·      inadequate administration, leading to the requirement to have the membership database rebuilt. The costs of such a rebuild have been known to be as large as R 20 million for a large umbrella fund.</para>

<para>·      choice of an incompetent or fraudulent service provider, for example,  when the Mineworker’s Provident Fund outsourced payment of widows’ pensions to Fidentia.</para>

 

<para>The loss arising from the accumulation of minor errors over time could reach 1% or 2% of a Fund’s total assets.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>3.4       Losses due to theft, fraud or dishonesty</title>

<para>Fraud is always possible while working with large sums of money, and possible losses from fraud could arise due to:</para>

<para>·        diversion of benefit payments from the proper beneficiary to the fraudster;</para>

<para>·        creation of dummy members and payment of their benefits to the fraudster;</para>

<para>·        arranging for contributions to be paid into a wrong account.</para>

 

<para>In general, such fraud is unlikely to exceed the benefit payable to an individual Member, or one month’s contributions for a Participating Employer. However, ongoing and small fraudulent transactions could accumulate to significant amounts over time.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>3.5       Losses due to computer crime</title>

<para>Most fraud in the pensions industry is likely to have some link with computer systems. Losses that are specific to computer systems can arise due to deliberate and malicious acts, or negligence, including the failure of computer systems and computers, and loss of data. Apart from any direct losses, such failures can lead to large costs related to reconstructing the database.</para>

<para>Business interruption for an extended period, while systems are restored or rebuilt, can have catastrophic consequences, not only for the Funds but also on the ability of the administrator to recover from the problem.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>3.6       Industry benchmarks</title>

<para>In the absence of any clear guidelines from the FSB, various suggestions regarding the quantum of cover have been made in the retirement industry including:</para>

<para>·     twice the largest death benefit;</para>

<para>·        2% of assets plus 10% of annual contributions; and</para>

<para>·     a minimum of R 1 000 000 per fund.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>3.7       Risk factors</title>

<para>The level of risk associated with a Fund can be gauged by considering various risk factors and good-governance principles. The FSB’s Circular PF 130 recommends several principles that should be adhered to in ensuring the good governance of retirement funds. Appendix B includes a template based on those principles.</para>

<para>The higher the level of risk associated with the governance and administration of a Fund, the greater the need for insurance. By managing these factors and actively taking steps to reduce and manage risk, the need for insurance can be reduced. The parallel with motor insurance is for the careful, competent driver to insure himself only for balance of third party, fire and theft, or obtain insurance with a very large excess. The careless, incompetent driver is well advised to find the most comprehensive insurance possible.</para>

<para>We suggest that the template in Appendix B be used to apply loadings to the recommended level of indemnity insurance cover to allow for any higher than average probability of risk to which, in the opinion of the Trustees, the Fund may be exposed.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title align="center">Section 4 – Recommendations</title>
<sect2>
<title>4.1       Current cover</title>

<para>Based on the latest renewal schedule, details of which is shown in Appendix         A, the indemnity cover in force in respect of the Fund is R{{InForceCover}}. </para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>4.2       Risk parameters</title>

<para>            Statistics from the Fund that provide guidelines to the amount of indemnity          insurance required are set out in the Table below.</para>

<para>Risk parameters</para>


<table border="4" >
<tr>     <td colspan="2" align="center"> Risk parameter	</td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Number of Members </td> <td> {{MemberNumber}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Annual Contributions </td> <td> R{{AnnualCons}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Value of investment </td> <td> R{{InvestmnetValue}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Largest death benefit sum assured </td> <td> R{{TopDth1}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Average of top ten death sums assured </td> <td> R{{AverageTopTenDeathBens}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Largest Member Share </td> <td> R{{Topshare1}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Average of top ten largest Member's Shares </td> <td> R{{AverageTopTenMemberShares}} </td> </tr>
</table>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>4.3       Recommended cover</title>

<para>Based on the information supplied, details of which are shown in Appendix A, we recommend that the indemnity cover in respect of the Fund be a minimum of R{{MinimumCover}}.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>           
<title>4.4       Loading</title>

<para>Based on the answers to the questions in the risk-loading template shown in Appendix B,  {{RecText}}</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>4.5       Disclaimer</title>

<para>Whatever sum assured is chosen, there remains the possibility that a claim may arise that exceeds the sum assured. The contents of this report should not be interpreted as a warranty that the recommended sum assured will be sufficient to meet any or all claims.</para>

<para>The higher the sum assured, the higher the premium will be. Premiums for indemnity cover will erode Members’ retirement savings. The Trustees should find a balance between affordable premiums and a sum assured that is likely to cover most eventualities.</para>

<para> The purpose of this report is to provide a reasonable benchmark that takes into account the relevant risk factors, and to alert the Trustees to factors that should be considered in determining the appropriate level of cover. The Trustees remain responsible for the final decision regarding the amount of cover to be obtained.</para>

<para>CA Scott</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title align="center">Appendix A : Information supplied</title>
<sect2>
<title>A.1      Details of information used in determining the basic cover</title>

<table border="4" >
<tr> <td colspan="2" align="center">Information</td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Schedule and Cover</td> <td> </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Period of insurance cover </td> <td> </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>- From </td> <td> {{CoverFrom}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>- To </td> <td> {{CoverTo}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Retroactive date </td> <td> {{RetroDate}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Annual premium </td> <td> R{{AnnualPremuim}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Limit of indemnity </td> <td> R{{InForceCover}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>First amount payable </td> <td> R{{Excess}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Any claims in last six years?  </td> <td> {{ClainsYN}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Highest claim made (if any) </td> <td> R{{HighestClaim}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Aggregate claim </td> <td> R{{AggregateClaim}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Data at </td> <td> </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Number of Members </td> <td> {{MemberNumber}}	</td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Annual Contributions </td> <td> R{{AnnualCons}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td>Value of investments </td> <td> R{{InvestmentValue}} </td></tr>
<tr> <td>Top ten death benefits sums assured </td> <td> </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 1th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth1}}</td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 2th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth2}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 3th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth3}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 4th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth4}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 5th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth5}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 6th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth6}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 7th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth7}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 8th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth8}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 9th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth9}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 10th - </td> <td> R{{TopDth10}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td> Top ten Member Shares </td> <td> </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 1th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare1}}	</td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 2th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare2}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 3th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare3}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 4th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare4}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 5th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare5}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 6th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare6}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 7th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare7}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 8th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare8}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 9th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare9}} </td> </tr>
<tr> <td align="Right"> 10th - </td> <td> R{{TopShare10}} </td> </tr>
</table>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title align="center">Appendix B : Risk loading template</title>
<sect2>
<title>B.1      Loading to be applied to basic cover</title>

<para>The templates included in this appendix are automated tools designed to assist the officers of the Fund in determining if the Fund is exposed to any higher than average probability of risk, taking into account the good governance principles set out in the FSB’s Circular PF 130. The purpose of the templates are twofold -</para>

<para>a)     to raise the awareness of the Board to any higher than average risks to which the Fund is exposed; and</para>

<para>b)     to calculate an appropriate loading (if any) to be applied to the basic indemnity cover recommended in Section 4.3.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
